Hello and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan and today we're going
to be diving further into equilibrium.
So this is a follow up video to my
last video on equilibrium which just
talked about the fundamental concepts
of how we can do k expressions, how, uh,
essentially with equilibrium we have a
forward and a reverse reaction and we
illustrate them using these expressions.
So this is going to go into a little
bit more of the theory behind it and how
all this comes about and how it works.
So when it comes to equilibrium,
really, the one thing that we got to
think about, it's all about achieving
balance within a chemical reaction,
meaning that it's sort of a battle
of the rates of the reaction between
the forward and the reverse reaction.
So we want to try to think of how can,
how can the reaction sort of achieve it?
Zen moment is one way to really.
to look at this.
So if I, let's say, have this
chemical reaction here, um, what
we're trying to actually understand
is, is it's, that reactions do not
react all the way to completion.
Even though up until this point in
general chemistry, you're always told,
Hey, all the reactants go to products.
That's not always the case.
In fact, most reactions generally fall
somewhere in the middle where you will
make a lot of products, but there's always
going to be reactants remaining left over.
Now this can be especially true
in terms of the solution phase.
and in gas phase reactions specifically.
Now, we typically don't do a lot of
calculations with like in terms of
stoichiometry with these or anything crazy
and introductory chemistry, but we do got
to realize that, hey, this entire process
is dynamic, meaning that's ever changing.
We can try to To essentially put different
stresses or change the conditions of
our reactions to help influence it.
Can we try to push it in
one way versus another?
So there's all kinds of ways you
can affect a reaction, right?
You can change the concentration.
You can increase the temperature a lot.
You could maybe add an
enzyme or a catalyst.
You could change the
pressure or the volume.
All these little things will have a
really big impact on this process.
Now, why are chemical reactions happening?
Well, when we were talking about
equilibrium is that they had a,
we have, we show these via aqueous
chemicals or gas phase chemicals.
So the more simple forms of chemicals,
especially when it comes to gases.
Now the way that we talk about all
this is kind of goes back to kinetic
molecular theory and that all these
little particles, they're like little
billiard balls hitting each other.
Okay.
Well, molecules collide with one another.
Now when they collide with
maybe another reactant, well
then a reaction will happen.
But the thing about it is it,
it's not just that simple.
It needs to be in the correct orientation.
It needs to have enough
energy for that to happen.
So one of the things that we need
to think about is when we're looking
at, let's say a flask like we have
a right here, like on the left with
all these different numbers here.
Depending on how many reactants
you have, it gives more and more
possibilities of collisions, right?
The more you increase it,
the probability goes up.
So the more things that we introduce, the
more possibility of collisions happening.
When a collision occurs,
The reaction occurs.
And that's one of the things
that we're trying to happen.
Same thing with temperature, right?
If you get these molecules and are really
excited and kind of running around,
it's sort of like if you give a five
year old a ton of sugar and then they're
just running and bouncing all over the
place, chemicals are the exact same way.
So when we are looking at these different
reactions, well, essentially, if you
take like, let's say like nitrogen and
oxygen here, Well, if they collide with
each other in the right orientation,
meaning they both line up with each
other in that horizontal, like I'm
showing here above, well, then it will
make nitrogen monoxide, but notice that
it has to be the right orientation.
It has to, they have to hit each other.
And then the reaction needs to occur.
So when it comes to equilibrium,
like this is what's occurring behind
the scenes is that the reactions
are coming in contact with each
other and having an effect, right?
And that that's what
it's sort of all about.
Now, when we go a little bit farther
into this, well, when the chemical
reaction occurs, I mentioned that it has
to have enough energy for it to happen
to, it needs to be heated up in a sense.
Um, so what this picture shows
is this is what we refer to
as a potential energy surface.
So on the left, you can
see the reactants, right?
So down here at the bottom,
you have nitrogen and oxygen.
Now for them to react, they had
to be in the right collision.
But, or sorry, the right
orientation, right?
They have to be like a sandwich
when they hit each other.
Now the thing about this though, they
need to have enough energy, meaning
it has to be moving fast enough for
them to smack each other and to react.
It needs to have a ton
of activation energy.
So when we look at these surfaces, they
start all the way down here with a little
bit of energy all the way at the bottom.
And the thing is, they need to
essentially climb this big mountain
in order for the reaction to happen.
So this is what we refer to as
a transition state, meaning that
it needs to have all this energy
and then in transition to make
the products, it will eventually
come back down and make products.
Now to get over this hump, it needs
to have enough energy to do it.
This is a very common picture that you
see in biology courses because when we're
referring to enzymes and using catalysts.
Essentially, the whole idea of your
body being able to work is that an
enzyme will lower this barrier and
make the reaction a little easier.
So not only does it have to be in like
the correct orientation, but it needs to
have enough energy for it to happen too.
So one thing to keep in mind is the
higher this barrier is, the harder
it is to happen, the slower it is.
And this is where rates come into, come
into mind, because essentially they're
related to the amount of collisions
occurring over the amount of time.
So the more, the more energy
that's required, the harder
it is for it to react.
But if you increase the temperature,
then it's going to make it a
lot easier for these to happen.
So this would be more likely to
happen at, let's say boiling,
let's say for water boiling, like
a water boiling temperature versus.
Let's say at a freezing or absolute
zero where nothing's really moving,
that plays a really big effect.
In terms of the application of things,
this is actually why electric cars and
hybrid cars really only work in certain
types of app types of environments.
One thing that you might realize
that if you maybe if you drive
a hybrid or if you have a friend
that even has an electric car.
is that they only really work
during very, very set of conditions.
They kind of like, what the way I
always joke with is they work really
well in a Los Angeles based condition
because it's always like 70 degrees.
Um, but if it's too cold, then or too
hot, these reactions work off collisions.
They are chemical processes
that's powering your batteries.
So if it's very, really cold
out, one thing you're going to
see is that the gas efficiency
of a hybrid is going to go down.
Same thing with the mile
range on an electric car.
Same thing if it's too hot as well,
you'll also see the same idea.
In fact, if you kind of actually
look at, let's say like Honda's, uh,
uh, since I pulled this off Honda's
website for their electric cars.
And the one thing that they show is that,
uh, batteries work, essentially it says
batteries work by chemical reaction and
the speed of the reaction decreases as the
temperature drops resulting in a temporary
decrease in total battery capacity.
So they advertise this right to
you that, Hey, these batteries,
they don't quite work all the time.
So this is something you got to kind
of realize this is a real world thing.
You can see it firsthand,
even in terms of.
How your car, car works, or even how just
regular everything, everyday life works.
Now the reverse, when you balanced the
chemical reaction, right, you said that
there's two HI's behind this thing.
If we balance it, what that's telling you
is that two of these guys got to collide
in order to make the reverse happen.
So it's all about how can they line up?
How can they collide to
make the reactions happen?
And that's what the k equations are
showing is, all right, what are, what's
the odds that's going to go forward
or reverse when it comes to it, right?
If it's a really small k value below
one, that's telling you that it's
going to mainly be reactants, right?
That the odds of them running
into each other, having enough
energy is not generally occurring.
Whereas the forward is kind
of like the opposite idea.
So if we were to practice this, let's
say to write out some K equations,
just so we can see for both the forward
and the reverse, could we do that?
Well, let, let's take a look at it.
So the first thing that we have to do
when it comes to writing a K equation
is typically we're looking at either
KC or KEQ when we're writing these.
So let's just use KC, which
is for just the concentration.
So the first thing was is that we
did the products over the reactants.
So we would write our CS
two, which is a product.
We will put that into brackets.
Now, being that it has a coefficient
of one, we don't need to worry
about writing a power, right?
But if you, just for just to show
you, right, it would just be a power
one because the coefficient is one.
Now, with H two on the products,
there are four of them.
So what we are going to do is we're gonna
write a power of four to help illustrate.
that we have that same power of four
that's up here, oops, that's up here
at the top, um, to help illustrate that
we, you need four of these different
things to collide, and the more of
them, the more, the more difficult
it is for this reaction to happen.
Now, on the other side, well, we
have our reactants, so we have
CH4, we'll put that in brackets,
and that's also to a power of one.
And then we have H2S, and that's two
eight, and that will be squared, and
that's due to the coefficient as well.
Now keep in mind that if you have to
write these in like something like
MyUpAndMath or an autograded program,
you're Then you don't want to include
the ones here, so you just write
it just like this to illustrate.
This should be for the forward
reaction to show the k value.
Now when it comes to the reverse,
essentially all we would do is we
would put kc, that would be to the
negative 1 to show the backwards.
And then all's you would, all's you
have to do is pretty much just flip
the products and the reactants.
So if I take my, uh, reactants
from before, I would just
pretty much just divide that by
what products were last time.
And we would flip these entire
things to show the forward.
and the reverse because they
are part of the same equation.
It's just referring to two
different ways to illustrate it.
What's the problem asking for?
Usually you only ever have to do the
top one, but if it ever asks you for the
reverse reactions rate, then technically
everything needs to flip when you're
showing those different processes.
Let's go on to our final little
tidbits and points about this.
Now, the most important thing to really
say is that when the rates of the reaction
is at the forward rate and the reverse
rate, when they're equal to each other,
that is when equilibrium is achieved.
It is when the rates are the same,
meaning that how, when we're making
reactants and when we're making products.
When it's essentially, it's not
changing anymore on each side
in terms of concentration, that
is when equilibrium is made.
So when we're looking at
these, so the last one was on
reactants, or sorry, on the rates.
This is on the concentrations.
The concentrations do not need to
be the same, just to say that again,
they don't need to be the same.
The only thing that happens
is that the rates equal out.
So one thing that you can kind of see
here is that as the rates, let's say if
I look at the forward reaction and you
see the rate is increasing, increasing,
increasing, the And then, and as it, as
it goes, the concentration is increasing,
but over time, it's just going to stop.
It's going to, the concentration
is not going to change anymore.
So with these, right, we're looking
at the products here and you can see,
Hey, this is the same versus when we
have our reactants, you can see that,
okay, it's converting into products
more and more is less, less reactants.
And then all of a sudden it stabilizes.
This is when equilibrium is achieved.
They do not need to be
equal to each other.
I can guarantee you that will
be a question either on a
homework or an exam somewhere.
Is that equilibrium is when the rates
equal, not when the concentrations,
the concentrations can equal each
other, but it's very, very, very
rare when that situation happens.
So when we're kind of
looking at these guys.
The whole entire thing is all about the
collisions that are occurring in terms
of the reaction that over the course of
time We will see reactants are going to be
converted to products So like for example,
if I like look here, I can see I have
eight reactants and no products and then
we can see it's slowly transitioning more
and more to products So, eventually, when
you see that it's not changing, that's
when you know equilibrium is occurring.
It's all about, like, can you get to
that, can you get to that final little,
little piece of where that happens?
If you see no more change, then
you made it to equilibrium.
And the final really big point, though,
about all this is that the system is
dynamic, meaning it's constantly changing.
New conditions are always
being applied to the reaction.
So it's always going to try to respond
it to that So let's try to take a look
at this demonstration that I found
online for you to watch and then I'll
talk over it So that way you can kind
of see how equilibrium works with a
real life example So it's not this and
wavy concept behind the entire process.
Alright, so in this video This is
from Kevin Dirksen who's a high school
chemistry teacher and he came up with a
really good Way to describe equilibrium
using a demonstration So what he's
actually showing here is he has a
bath essentially with reactants that's
completely full and then with products and
what he's going to be doing with beakers
is showing the rate of the reactions.
So the reactants are going to be
converting to products and he's going
to keep exchanging these things.
Now, one thing you notice is that the
products beaker is pretty much empty.
The reactants one is completely full.
So what are you expecting is that, well,
over time you're going to be creating a
lot of products as this continues to go.
Now as he keeps transferring, one
thing that you're going to be able to
see is that, well, with each beaker,
he's going to only be able to fill
them so much because there's only so
much reactant and product available.
Now, one thing that you can
actually see here is that.
Equilibrium will is actually
getting achieved right now.
Notice how he's transferring both of
these with the same exact at the same
exact rate on both sides and the levels of
the containers are not changing anymore.
One of them started completely full.
The other one started empty.
So what this just demonstrates is that
equilibrium has occurred where both of
the concentrations are actually equal.
Notice how they both are transferring
250 milliliters at the same time.
So they both have the exact same rate of
reaction as they're being transferred.
This is equilibrium, right?
Even though the forward reaction was
being favored throughout the entire
beginning, eventually they began
to transfer at the exact same rate,
which is what, what we are looking for
when we are looking at equilibrium.
No matter how much He attempts to do this,
there's no possible way for it to ever
get out of this state, which is really
the really exciting part about this.
So let's take a look at
this next example with this.
Now with this, one thing you can
see, it's going to actually equal
that chart where you can see the
rates are equal to each other.
So that's what I was showing you earlier.
So this is what it's demonstrating.
The rates became equal
in terms of the reaction.
Now, what if we end up
changing the conditions of
how we're transferring things?
So what if you decided to on one
container have a bigger beaker and
then on the other one, you wanted to
have a really tiny beaker, meaning
like, okay, let's say one side is a
little bit more favored than the other.
Well, what exactly would happen
in terms of that reaction and
that's what he's going to be
doing in this next demonstration
So here you can see on the left.
He has a 300 milliliter
beaker and on the right.
He has about a hundred and fifty
milliliter beaker So what he's going
to be doing is transferring them
and you can think like, all right.
Well, there's no possible
way that the reactant side is
ever not going to lose, right?
He's transferring way more liquid
at a time on the, on the left
hand side versus the right.
Now, the thing about this though,
is depending on how much reactant
is in product is available.
Well, he's only going to be
able to realistically fill up.
So notice that now you can kind of see
the levels aren't changing anymore,
so this is telling you that, oh,
he's actually achieving equilibrium
when he zooms in on the beakers.
Notice that the volumes are the same, so
they're both 100 about 140 milliliters.
Even though the beakers are
different sizes, the rates
are now equal to each other.
He's transferring at the same rate.
140 milliliters, 140
milliliters each time.
So Essentially, because of these
rates being equal to each other,
equilibrium has been achieved,
which is incredible to see, right?
So with just a simple demonstration.
You can see this is how equilibrium
would work in a real life application.
So let's look at the final
chart just to explain this.
So in the very end, we can see that
equilibrium is finished, and the whole
idea here is that, well, the equilibrium
is essentially, is being reached here,
and the amounts do not need to be the
same for equilibrium to meet, right?
So it's just when the rates
of the reaction are equal.
Not necessarily when the
concentrations are equal.
And that's the important thing to realize.
That's the final take home with that.
Alright?
So, that's the whole
thing with this video.
So that's the final end of it.
Um, with this I might be making
another practice problem video to help
you kind of fully understand all the
little intricacies of how to use these.
But I hope this kind of filled in the
gaps for what exactly is the theory
behind equal to equilibrium process.
Thank you so much for listening.
I hope that this video
helped a little bit.
Try to fill in those little gaps.
If you're confused, please feel free
to reach out and send me an email.
Send me a message.
Or comment below in the
video, you can do that too.
Um, if you are, if you're not one
of my normal students and you are
watching this video to help you with
your class, please hit that like and
subscribe button and help the video
grow and help the channel grow as well.
Alright, thank you so much for listening.
This has been Dr.
Dan and if you need more help with
chemistry, please let me know.
I'll see you all later.
Bye now.